Salman Shahzad

Dudley, United Kingdom +44 7380205441 / salman.shahzad100@gmail.com

About

With two years in engineering, one year in data analysis, and one year in Ruby on Rails development, I offer a comprehensive skill set. Grounded in engineering principles, I'm enthusiastic about leveraging my technical expertise to drive innovation in the industry. Excited to contribute meaningfully to engineering projects and advance within the field.

Education

University of Bradford

BACHELORS ELECTRICAL & ELECTRONIC ENGINEERING

Sep 2015-Dec 2019

IELTS 7.0 First Aid

Work Experience

Data Analyst, Viral Square

Oct 2022-Oct 2023

- Collect, clean and integrate data from diverse sources (MySQL, PostgreSQL, APIs, spreadsheets) to form complete datasets for analysis.
- Analyze large datasets using Python's matplotlib or Tableau, and effectively communicate insights with clear visualizations and dashboards to stakeholders.
- Facilitated data-driven approaches, resulting in a 15% increase in retention and a 40% satisfaction improvement.

Associate Software Engineer, Viral Square

Aug 2022-Sept 2022

- Develop and maintain Ruby on Rails web apps, adhering to coding standards and utilizing gems to meet project requirements.
- Design, implement, and optimize database schemas with ActiveRecord and PostgreSQL,
 while also developing robust RESTful APIs for seamless integration.

Ruby on Rails Developer, Next Frontier Labs Nov 2021 – July 2022

- MVC architecture, database management, and UI development experience through Ruby on Rails projects and a Udemy course.
- Designed, coded, and debugged complex web apps using Ruby on Rails, collaborating with the team to deepen understanding of the software development lifecycle.

Shift Supervisor, Philip Morris International

- **June 2020 Aug 2021**
- Ensured uninterrupted operation of facility utilities (HVAC, Chemical, Powerhouse,
 Waste Water, Primary, Secondary), optimizing efficiency and overseeing KPIs.
- Implemented Daily Direction System (DDS) to streamline team workflow.
- Conducted Initial Problem Solving (IPS), IIRs, and defect handling to prevent future anomalies.
- Conducted internal audits of utilities to ensure safety compliance, including permit signing and safety checks before work commencement to enhance protocols.

Assistant Shift Incharge, Atlas Honda

Mar 2020 - June 2020

- Oversaw power plant operations to ensure uninterrupted power supply.
- Managed generator parameters and load according to mill's standards, overseeing Jenbacher 320 and 420 gensets.

Operations Trainee, SkyElectric

Sep 2019 - Mar 2020

 Participated in installation, net metering, locality surveys, and SketchUp sketches for optimal solutions.

Assistant Electrician, Namal Institute Mianwali Feb 2019-Mar 2019

Engaged in wiring plugs and providing assistance with electrical repairs and fittings.

Lab Assistant, Namal Institute Mianwali

Nov 2017-Dec 2018

• Check in the logs of lab instruments and to trouble shoot them if necessary.

Volunteer Teacher, Namal Institute Mianwali Jan 2016 -Apr 2016.

Instructed intermediate students in Mathematics at Namal under NSSI for 3 months.

Projects

- 1) https://salman-shahzad.github.io/Salman.github.io/
- 2) Human Following Robot (Final Year Project, Bachelors)
 - a) Made a robotic Car that follows a human being using Kinect & Aurdino.
- 3) Smart standalone temperature system
 - a) Developed an embedded standalone system for real-time monitoring of temperature and humidity, triggering alarms as required.
- 4) Group project Health monitoring system
 - a) Developed a wearable system for monitoring heart rate and cadence.

Skills

• Solar System Design, Proteus, Circuit Design, Arduino, Matlab, MiniTab

- Ruby, Ruby on Rails, GitHub, HTML
- Data Modelling, Python, Tableau, PowerBI, SQL, Postgresql, Active Record, API integration, Data Manipulation, Pandas, Numpy, Data Warehouse, Data Cleaning.